Guide to the Albert Selden Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Albert Selden papers
1922-1983
YCAL MSS 866
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
10.92
(24 boxes) + 1 art
Selden, Albert
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Mrs. Albert Selden, 1988.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Albert Selden (1922-1987)
Albert Wiggin Selden was born in 1922 in New York City, and graduated from Yale University in 1943. During World War II he served as a first lieutenant in the United States Army, and was the recipient of the Bronze Star. He was an investor in and composer and producer of Broadway and regional theater productions, beginning with the show Small Wonder in 1948. Other productions with which he was associated include A Month of Sundays (1951), The Grey Eyed People (1952), The Amazing Adele (1955), The Body Beautiful (1958), The Girls Against the Boys (1959), Man of La Mancha (1965), Hallelujah, Baby! (1967), and Irene (1974). Selden was instrumental in the restoration of the Goodspeed Opera House in East Haddam, Connecticut, and served as its managing director when the theater reopened in 1963. He co-produced the world premiere of Man of La Mancha at the Goodspeed in 1965. The production went on to open on Broadway where it won multiple Tony Awards including best musical of 1966. In 1968 he won the Tony Award for best producer of a musical, Hallelujah, Baby!, which also won the best musical award. Selden died in Santa Fe, New Mexico in 1987.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of material documenting Albert Selden's career as a composer and producer of musical and dramatic theater productions including typescript and manuscript playscripts and music scores by Selden and others; scrapbooks containing photographs, clippings and memorabilia relating to Selden's family and his theatrical career including Man of La Mancha and the Goodspeed Opera House; production window cards and programs; and published songbooks and music scores.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged by type of material.
Composers -- United States; Musicals -- United States; Musicals -- Scores; Theater -- Production and direction -- United States; Theatrical producers and directors -- United States; Scripts (documents) -- United States -- 20th Century; Theater posters -- United States -- 20th Century; Composers -- United States -- 20th Century; Theatrical producers and directors -- United States -- 20th Century; Selden, Albert; Goodspeed Opera House
- Scripts by Albert Selden
  - "The Amazing Adele", undated; 3 (Box 1)
  - "A Month of Sundays", undated; 3 (Box 1)
- Scripts by others
  - "Abraham's Mask", undated; 3 (Box 1)
  - "After You, Mr. Hyde", undated (Box 1)
  - "Amerika", 1981 (Box 1)
  - "...And Presumed Dead", undated (Box 1)
  - "The Art Gallery", 1979 (Box 1)
  - "As the Lady Said to the Sailor...", undated (Box 1)
  - "The Better Mousetrap", 1957 (Box 1)
  - "The Body Beautiful", 1957 (Box 1)
  - "The Booties of Butternut Hill", undated (Box 1)
  - "Canto XI", undated; 2 (Box 1)
  - "Canzada and the Boys", 1976 (Box 1)
  - "Christmas is Comin' Uptown", undated (Box 2)
  - "Climb the Greased Pole", 1978 (Box 2)
  - "Come Summer", 1968 (Box 2)
  - "Craters", undated (Box 2)
  - "The Deep End", undated (Box 2)
  - "Engaged!", undated; 2 (Box 2)
    Scope and Contents
    Includes master production book.
  - "Even Steven", undated; 3 (Box 2)
  - "The Facts of Life", undated (Box 2)
  - "The Fair and Unfair Sex", undated; 2 (Box 2)
  - "Gomes", undated (Box 2)
  - "The Guy with the Flashlight", 1977; 2 (Box 2)
  - "Halloween", 1971, 1973; 2 (Box 2)
  - "Halloween", 1971, 1973; 3 (Box 3)
    Includes prompt script.
  - "Happily Ever After", undated (Box 3)
  - "A Hero's Song", 1974 (Box 3)
  - "Holiday", undated; 3 (Box 3)
  - "His and Hers", undated (Box 3)
  - "Irene", 1972-1976, undated; 6 (Box 3)
  - "King of the Boys", 1977 (Box 3)
  - "Life Support", 1982 (Box 4)
  - "A Likely Tale", undated (Box 4)
  - "The Lincoln Mask", 1972; 2 (Box 4)
  - "Love in a Piano Roll Factory", 1983 (Box 4)
  - "Maggie", undated (Box 4)
  - "Man of La Mancha", 1961, undated; 3 (Box 4)
  - "Merton of the Movies", 1977, undated; 2 (Box 4)
  - "Murder at the Gaiety", undated (Box 4)
  - "On Time", undated (Box 4)
  - "Padre Don Camillo", 1968 (Box 4)
  - "A Palm Tree in a Rose Garden", undated (Box 4)
  - "The Plaster Bambino", undated (Box 4)
  - "Pocahontas", undated; 2 (Box 4)
    Includes outline.
  - "Rashomon", undated (Box 4)
  - "So Long, 174th Street", 1975; 2 (Box 4)
  - "Straitjacket", undated; 2 (Box 4)
  - "The Three-Toed Pony", undated (Box 5)
  - "To Sit on a Horse", undated; 3 (Box 5)
  - "Tricks of the Trade", 1977-1978; 4 (Box 5)
  - "The Utter Glory of Morrissey Hall", 1978 (Box 5)
  - "A Very Special Baby", undated (Box 5)
  - "Waiting for Gillian", undated; 2 (Box 5)
  - "The Waterbury Tales", undated; 2 (Box 5)
  - "What Do You Really Know About Your Husband?", undated; 4 (Box 5)
- Production programs, 1948-1983, undated (Box 6)
- Music
  - Christmas Songs and More, undated (Box 6)
  - Dear Santa: 53 Christmas Songs and Original Children's Letters to Santa (New York: The Big 3 Music Corporation), undated (Box 6)
  - A Treasury of Chistmas Songs and Carols (Boston: Houghton Mifflin Company), 1955 (Box 6)
  - Too Many Songs by Tom Lehrer With Not Enough Drawings by Ronald Searle (New York: Pantheon Books), 1981 (Box 6)
  - Vocal scores, 1948-1955 (Box 6)
  - Unidentifed manuscript and typescript lyrics, undated; 3 (Box 6)
  - Manuscript music scores, undated (Box 6)
  - Blank music manuscript notebooks (Box 6)
  - Music scores
    - "The Amazing Adele", undated; 4 (Box 7 (Oversize))
    - "The Amazing Adele", undated; 5 (Box 8 (Oversize))
    - "The Girls Against the Boys", undated (Box 9 (Oversize))
    - "The Utter Glory of Morrissey Hall", 1979 (Box 9 (Oversize))
      Includes reproductions of set and costume designs
- Scrapbooks
  - Productions
    - "Comin' Uptown", 1979-1980 (Box 10 (Oversize))
    - "The Girls Against the Boys", 1958-1959 (Box 11 (Oversize))
    - "His and Hers", 1953 (Box 12 (Oversize))
    - "His and Hers", 1954 (Box 13 (Oversize))
    - "Irene", 1972-1973 (Box 14 (Oversize))
    - "Irene", 1972-1973 (Box 15)
    - "Man of La Mancha", 1966-1967 (Box 16 (Oversize))
    - "Man of La Mancha", 1967-1970 (Box 17 (Oversize))
    - "Man of La Mancha", 1965-1970 (Box 18 (Oversize))
    - "Man of La Mancha", 1965-1969 (Box 19 (Oversize))
    - "Small Wonder", 1948-1949 (Box 20 (Oversize))
  - Other
    - Goodspeed Opera House, 1964 (Box 21 (Oversize))
    - Family photograph album, 1922-1937 (Box 22 (Oversize))
- Window Cards
  - The Amazing Adele, undated (Box 23 (Oversize))
  - The Body Beautiful, undated (Box 23 (Oversize))
  - Come Summer, undated (Box 23 (Oversize))
  - Comin' Uptown, undated (Box 23 (Oversize))
  - The Girls Against the Boys, undated (Box 23 (Oversize))
  - The Grey-Eyed People, undated (Box 23 (Oversize))
  - Hallelujah, Baby!, undated (Box 23 (Oversize))
  - His and Hers, undated (Box 23 (Oversize))
  - Irene (with Debbie Reynolds), undated (Box 24 (Oversize))
  - Irene (with Jane Powell) (Box 24 (Oversize))
  - The Lincoln Mask, undated (Box 24 (Oversize))
  - Man of La Mancha (ANTA Washington Square Theatre), undated (Box 24 (Oversize))
  - Man of La Mancha (Vivian Beaumont Theatre), undated (Box 24 (Oversize))
  - Portrait of a Queen, undated (Box 24 (Oversize))
  - Small Wonder, undated (Box 24 (Oversize))
  - The Utter Glory of Morrissey Hall, undated (Box 24 (Oversize))
  - Wating for Gillian, undated (Box 24 (Oversize))
  - What Do You Really Know About Your Husband?, undated (Box 24 (Oversize))
- Art work
  - [Woman in flower garden], goache on paper, undated (Box 25 (Art))